<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- comment -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-mmusic-4572-update-02.txt" updates="4572" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title>
		Updates to RFC 4572
	</title>
    <author fullname="Christer Holmberg" initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg">
        <organization abbrev="Ericsson">Ericsson</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
                <city>Jorvas</city>
                <region></region>
                <code>02420</code>
                <country>Finland</country>
            </postal>
            <phone></phone>
            <email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2016" />
    <area>RAI</area>
    <abstract>
        <t>
            This document defines a new SDP attribute, 'fpl', which can be used by SDP
            offerers and answerers to carry fingerprints associated with a certificate.
        </t>
		<t>
            This document updates RFC 4572 by clarifying the usage of multiple SDP 'fingerprint'
            attributes with a single TLS connection. The document also updates the preferred
            cipher suite to be used, and removes the requirement to use the same hash function
            for calculating the certificate fingerprint that is used to calculate the
            certificate signature.
        </t>
    </abstract>
</front>
<middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
        <t>
            RFC 4572 <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4572"/> specifies
            how to establish Transport Layer Security (TLS) connections using
            the Session Description Protocol (SDP) <xref format="default" pageno="false"
            target="RFC4566"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
            RFC 4572 defines the SDP 'fingerprint' attribute, which is used to carry a secure hash
            value (fingerprint) associated with a certificate. However, RFC 4572 is currently unclear on whether
            multiple 'fingerprint' attributes can be associated with a single SDP media description ("m= line")
            <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4566"/>, and the associated semantics.
            Multiple fingerprints are needed if an endpoints wants to provide multiple fingerprints associated
            with a single certificate, or if an endpoints wants to provide fingerprints associated with
            multiple certificate. For example, with RTP-based media, an endpoint might use different 
            certificates for RTP and RTCP.
        </t>
        <t>
            RFC 4572 also specifies a preferred cipher suite. However, the currently preferred
            cipher suite is considered outdated, and the preference needs to be updated.
        </t>
        <t>
            RFC 4572 mandates that the hash function used to calculate the fingerprint is the same
            hash function used to calculate the certificate signature. That requirement might
            prevent usage of newer, stronger and more collision-safe hash functions for calculating
            certificate fingerprints. This change also requires that multiple 'fingerprint' attributes can
            be associated with a single "m=" line, so that implementations are able to provide hashes
            generated with updated hash functions alongside those that are needed to interoperate
            with existing implementations.
        </t>
		<t>
            This document updates RFC 4572 <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4572"/>
            by clarifying the usage of multiple SDP 'fingerprint' attributes. It is clarified that
            multiple 'fingerprint' attributes can be used to carry fingerprints, calculated using
            different hash functions, associated with a given certificate, but the attribute cannot
            be used to carry fingerprints associated with multiple certificates.
        </t>
        <t>
            This document also defines a new SDP attribute, 'fpl', which can be used to carry multiple
            fingerprints associated with a single certificate.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions">
		<t>
			The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
			"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
			document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.
		</t>
    </section>

    
    <section title="SDP fpl Attribute" anchor="sec-fpl-attr">
        <section title="General" anchor="sec-fpl-attr-gen">
            <t>
                The SDP 'fpl' (abbreviation of FingerPrint List) attribute is used to carry one or 
                many fingerprints associated with a certificate. Any given attribute instance can 
                only be associated with a single certificate. Multiple 'fpl' attributes can be associated
                with a given SDP media description ("m=" line) in order to carry fingerprints associated 
                with multiple certificates.
            </t>
            <t>
                NOTE: The difference between the SDP 'fpl' attribute and the  SDP 'fingerprint' attribute
                <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4572"/>and the SDP 'fpl' is that the 'fpl' 
                attribute can be used to associate multiple fingerprints (calculated using different hash functions) 
                with a certificate. The 'fingerprint' attribute can only be used to carry a single fingerprint.
            </t>
            <t>
                When an endpoint matches
            
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Syntax" anchor="sec-fpl-attr-syn">
            <figure>
                <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

    attribute              =/ fingerprint-list

    fingerprint-list       =  "fpl" ":" hash-func SP fingerprint 
                                        *(":" hash-func SP fingerprint)
                        
    ;hash-func is defined in RFC 4572
    ;fingerprint is defined in RFC 4572
   
    Example:
    
    a=fpl:SHA-1 \
          4A:AD:B9:B1:3F:82:18:3B:54:02:12:DF:3E:5D:49:6B:19:E5:7C:AB \
          SHA-256 \
          4A:AD:B9:B1:3F:82:18:3B:54:02:12:DF:3E:5D:49:6B:19:E5:7C:AB

   
                ]]></artwork>
            </figure>        
            <t>
                There is no default value defined for the SDP 'fpl' attribute.
                Implementations that wish to use the attribute MUST explicitly include it
                in SDP offers and answers.
            </t>
            <t>
                The 'fpl' attribute may be either a session-level or a media-
                level SDP attribute. If it is a session-level attribute, it applies
                to all SDP media descriptions ("m=" lines) with which no media-level 
                'fpl' attribute has been associated.
            </t>
            <t>
                The mux category <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-sdp-mux-attributes"/> 
                for the 'fpl' attribute is 'IDENTICAL', which means that
                the attribute value must be identical across all media descriptions
                being multiplexed <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-sdp-bundle-negotiation"/>.
            </t>
            <t>
                For SDP media descriptions ("m=" lines) describing RTP-based media, the 'fpl' 
                attribute applies to the whole media description. The attribute MUST NOT be 
                defined per source (using the SDP 'ssrc' attribute <xref format="default" 
                pageno="false" target="RFC5576"/>). 
            </t>
            <t>
                The SDP Offer/Answer <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3264"/> 
                procedures associated with the attribute are defined in <xref target="sec-oa"/>
            </t>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section title="SDP Offer/Answer Procedures" anchor="sec-oa">
        <section title="General">
            <t>
                This section defines the SDP Offer/Answer procedures for the SDP 'fpl' attribute.
                The procedures are defined for any SDP media description ("m=" line) describing
                TLS/DTLS protected media.
            </t>
        </section>
        
        <section title="Generating the Initial SDP Offer" anchor="sec-oa-offer">
            <t>   
                When the offerer sends the initial offer, it MUST associate
                one or more SDP 'fpl' attributes with an SDP media description 
                ("m=" line) describing TLS/DTLS protected media. Each attribute
                contains one or more fingerprint values calculated for a given
                certificate.
            </t>
            <t>
                In addition, the offerer MAY associate one or more 
                SDP 'fingerprint' attributes with the "m=" line, according to 
                the procedures in <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4572"/>.
            </t>
            <t>
                If the offerer associates both 'fpl' attributes and 'fingerprint' 
                attributes with the "m=" line in the offer, the fingerprint value included in any
                'fingerprint' attribute MUST also be included in the 'fpl' attribute 
                associated with the same certificate.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Generating the Answer">       
            <t>
                When an answerer receives an offer that contains one or more
                SDP 'fpl' attributes, and if the answerer accepts the "m=" line,
                the answerer MUST associate one or more 'fpl' attributes with the
                corresponding "m=" line in the answer.
            </t>
            <t>
                If the offer does not contain any 'fpl' attribute, the answerer
                SHOULD NOT associate any 'fpl' attribute with the corresponding
                "m=" line in the answer.
            </t>
            <t>
                If the offer contains one or more SDP 'fingerprint' attributes, 
                the answerer follows the procedures in <xref format="default" pageno="false" 
                target="RFC4572"/> for generating the answer.
            </t>
            <t>
                If the answerer associates both 'fpl' attributes and 'fingerprint' 
                attributes with the "m=" line in the answer, the fingerprint value included in any
                'fingerprint' attribute MUST also be included in the 'fpl' attribute 
                associated with the same certificate.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Offerer Processing of the SDP Answer">
            <t>
                TBD
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Modifying the Session">
            <t>
                When an offerer sends a subsequent offer, and the offerer does not explicitly
                requests a new TLS connection/DTLS association to be established, the offerer
                MUST associate SDP 'fpl' attribute(s) that include the hash values associated
                with the previously negotiated TLS connection/DTLS association. The offerer
                MUST NOT associate SDP 'fpl' attributes including fingerprints for non-uses 
                certificates.
            </t>
            <t>
                When an offerer sends a subsequent offer, if the offerer explicitly requests
                a new TLS connection/DTLS association to be established, the offerer follow
                the procedures in <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="sec-oa-offer"/>.
            </t>
            <t>
                <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4572"/> describes the procedures
                for negotiating a new TLS connection.
            </t>
            <t>
                [ref-to-draft-dtls-sdp] describes the procedures for negotiating a new DTLS association.
            </t>            
        </section>
	</section>
     
    <section title="Update to RFC 4572">
        <t>
            This section updates section 5 of RFC 4572.
        </t>
        <section title="Update to the sixth paragraph of section 5">
            <figure>
                <artwork align="left" alt="" height="" name="" type="" width="" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[

OLD TEXT:

   A certificate fingerprint MUST be computed using the same one-way
   hash function as is used in the certificate's signature algorithm.
   (This ensures that the security properties required for the
   certificate also apply for the fingerprint.  It also guarantees that
   the fingerprint will be usable by the other endpoint, so long as the
   certificate itself is.)  Following RFC 3279 [7] as updated by RFC
   4055 [9], therefore, the defined hash functions are 'SHA-1' [11]
   [19], 'SHA-224' [11], 'SHA-256' [11], 'SHA-384' [11], 'SHA-512' [11]
   , 'MD5' [12], and 'MD2' [13], with 'SHA-1' preferred.  A new IANA
   registry of Hash Function Textual Names, specified in Section 8,
   allows for addition of future tokens, but they may only be added if
   they are included in RFCs that update or obsolete RFC 3279 [7].
   Self-signed certificates (for which legacy certificates are not a
   consideration) MUST use one of the FIPS 180 algorithms (SHA-1,
   SHA-224, SHA-256, SHA-384, or SHA-512) as their signature algorithm,
   and thus also MUST use it to calculate certificate fingerprints.


NEW TEXT:

   Following RFC 3279 [7] as updated by RFC 4055 [9], therefore, the
   defined hash functions are 'SHA-1' [11] [19], 'SHA-224' [11],
   'SHA-256' [11], 'SHA-384' [11], 'SHA-512' [11], 'MD5' [12], and
   'MD2' [13], with 'SHA-256' preferred.  A new IANA registry of Hash
   Function Textual Names, specified in Section 8, allows for addition
   of future tokens, but they may only be added if they are included
   in RFCs that update or obsolete RFC 3279 [7].

                ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section title="New paragraphs to the end of section 5">
                    <figure>
                <artwork align="left" alt="" height="" name="" type="" width="" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[


NEW TEXT:

    Multiple SDP fingerprint attributes can be associatd with an m-
    line, in order to carry fingerprints calculated using
    different hash functions for a given cerfificiate. All fingerprints
    carried in SDP fingerprint attributes, associated with a given m- line,
    MUST be associated with the same certificate.
    
    In some cases endpoints want to provide fingerprints 
    associated with multiple cerficiates (e.g. if separate certificates
    are used for RTP and RTCP). In such cases, endpoints MUST use the 
    mechanism in <ref-to-this-draft> in order to provide them
    to the peer.
    
    An endpoint MUST be able to match at least one of the received
    fingerprints with the used cerficiate. If there is no match, 
    the endpoint MUST NOT establish the TLS connection.    
    
    NOTE: The SDP fingerprint attribute does not contain a reference to
    a specific certificate. Endpoints need to compare the fingerprint
    with a certificate hash in order to look for a match.

                ]]></artwork>
            </figure>

        </section>
	</section>

	<section title="Security Considerations">
		<t>
            This document improves security. It updates the preferred hash function cipher suite
            from SHA-1 to SHA-256. By clarifying the usage and handling of multiple fingerprints, the
            document also enables hash agility, and incremental deployment of newer, and more secure,
            cipher suites.
		</t>
	</section>

    <section anchor="section.iana" title="IANA Considerations">
        <t>
            This document makes no requests from IANA.
        </t>
	</section>

	<section title="Acknowledgements">
		<t>
            Martin Thomson, Paul Kyzivat, Jonathan Lennox and Roman Shpount provided valuable comments and input on this document.
        </t>
	</section>

	<section title="Change Log">
		<t>[RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please remove this section when publishing]</t>
            <t>Changes from draft-ietf-mmusic-4572-update-01
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>Changes based on comments from Martin Thomson.</t>
                    <t>- Editorial fixes</t>
                    <t>New SDP 'fpl' attribuge added.</t>
                    <t></t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t>Changes from draft-ietf-mmusic-4572-update-00
			    <list style="symbols">
                    <t>Changes in handling of multiple fingerprints.</t>
                    <t>- Number of fingerprints calculated for each certificate does not have to match.</t>
                    <t>- Clarified that receiver shall check check fingerprints using hash algorithms it considers safe.</t>
                    <t>- Additional text added to security considerations section.</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t>Changes from draft-holmberg-mmusic-4572-update-01
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>Adopted WG document (draft-ietf-mmusic-4572-update-00) submitted.</t>
                    <t>IANA considerations section added.</t>
                </list>
            </t>
	</section>
</middle>
<back>
    <references title="Normative References">
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3264"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4572"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4566"?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5576"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-mmusic-sdp-mux-attributes-12"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-mmusic-sdp-bundle-negotiation-29"?>
    </references>
</back>
</rfc>
